[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
welcome all to this episode of software
engineering radio
our topic today is building of a sas
application and our guest is kumara
mayar kumar is the cto of the planning
business unit at workday
kumar has experience at data management
companies like illustra informix ariba
and oracle and now sas at workday
welcome kumar so glad to have you here
is there something you'd like to add to
your bio before we start thanks kanchen
for the opportunity to discuss this
important topic of sas applications in
the cloud no i think you covered it all
i just want to add
i do have deep experience in planning
but last several years i've been
delivering planning applications in the
cloud first at oracle now at workday
i mean there's a lot of interesting
things people are doing distributed
computing and cloud deployment have come
a long way
i'm learning a lot every day from my
amazing co-workers
and also there's a lot of strong
literature out there and
well-established design patterns
i'm happy to share many of my learnings
in this today's session
thank you so let's start with just a
basic design of how a sas application is
deployed
and the key terms that i've heard of
there are the control plane and the data
plane can you talk more about the
division of labor and between the
control plane and data plane and how
does that correspond to deploying of the
application yeah so before we get there
let's
talk about what is the modern standard
way of deploying applications in the
cloud
so it's all based on what we call as a
services architecture and services are
deployed as containers and often as a
docker container and using kubernetes
deployment
so
first we containerize all the
applications and then these containers
are put together in what is called a pod
a part can contain one or more
containers and these parts are then run
in what is called a node which is
basically the physical machine where the
execution happens
then all these
nodes
there are one or more nodes in what is
called the cluster
and then you go on to other higher order
concepts like regions and what not so
the basic architecture is cluster node
parts and containers so you can have a
very simple deployment like one cluster
one node one part and one container from
there we can go on to have hundreds of
clusters within each cluster hundreds of
nodes and within each node lots of parts
and even scale outpods
and replicated parts and so on and
within each part you can have lots of
containers so how do you manage this
level of complexity and scale
because
not only that you can have a
multi-tenant where with multiple
customers running on all of these so
luckily we have this control plane which
allows us to define policies for
networking and routing decision
monitoring of cluster events and
responding to them scheduling of these
parts when they go down how we bring it
up or how many we bring up and so on and
there are several other controllers that
are part of the control plane so it's a
declarative semantics and kubernetes
allows us to do that through just simply
specifying those policies
data plane is where the actual execution
happens so it's important to get a
control plane data plane
the roles and responsibilities correct
in a well-defined architecture so often
some companies try to write a lot of the
control plane logic in their own code
which should be completely avoided and
we should leverage a lot of the
out-of-the-box software
that not only comes with kubernetes but
also the other associated software
and all the effort should be focused on
data plane because if you start putting
a lot of code around control plane as
the kubernetes evolves or all the other
software evolves which have been proven
in many other sas vendors you won't be
able to take advantage of it because you
will be stuck with
all the logic you have put in for
control plane
so
and also this level of complexity lead
needs very formal methods to reason
about kubernetes provides that formal
methods
one should take advantage of that i'm
happy to answer any other questions here
on this while we're defining the terms
though let's continue and talk maybe
next about site card and also about
service mesh so that we have a little
bit of a foundation for later in the
discussion so let's start with sidecar
yeah when we learn about java and see
like there are a lot of design patterns
we learned right in the programming
language
similarly sidecar is an architectural
pattern for
cloud deployment in kubernetes or or
other similar deployment architecture
so it's a separate container that runs
alongside the application container in
the kubernetes part kind of unlike an
helper application this often comes in
handy to enhance a legacy code
let's say you have a monolithic legacy
application and that got converted into
a service and deployed as a container
and let's say we didn't do a good job
and we quickly converted that into a
container now you need to add a lot of
additional capabilities to make it run
well in a
kubernetes environment and sidecar
container allows us for that you can put
a lot of the additional logic
in the sidecar that enhances the
application container
some of the examples are
logging messaging monitoring
and tls
service discovery and many other things
which we can talk about later on so
sidecar is a is an important pattern
that helps with the cloud deployment
what about service mesh so why do we
need service mesh let's say once you
start containerizing you may start with
one two and quickly it will become three
four five and
many many services so once it gets to a
non-trivial number of services the
management of service to service
communication and many other aspects of
service management becomes very
difficult it's almost like an order n
square problem so how do you remember
what is the host name and the port
number or the ip address of one service
how do you establish service to service
trust and so on so to help with this
so service mesh notion has been
introduced from what i understand
lyft the car company first introduced
because when they were implementing
their sas application it became pretty
non-trivial so they wrote this code and
then they contributed to the public
domain so it since has become pretty
standard so istio is one of the popular
service mesh for enterprise cloud
deployment so it hides all the
complexities from the service itself so
the service can focus on its core logic
and then lets the
mesh deal with the service to service
issues
so what exactly happens is in istio
in the data plane every service is
augmented with the sidecar like which we
just talked about they call it an ny
which is a proxy and these proxies
mediate and control
all the network communications between
the microservices
they also collect and report telemetry
on all the mesh traffic so this way that
the core service can focus on its
business function it almost becomes part
of the control plane so the control
plane now manages and configures the
proxies they talk with the proxy so the
data plane doesn't directly talk to the
control plane but the sidecar proxy ny
talks to the control plane to route all
the traffic
this allows us to
do number of things for example in istio
cny
sidecar it can do number of
functionality like dynamic service
discovery load balancing it can perform
the duty of a tls termination it can act
like a circuit breaker can do health
check it can do fault injection it can
do all the metric collections logging
and it can perform number of things so
basically you can see that if there is a
legacy application which became
container without actually reacting or
re writing the code we can suddenly
enhance the application container with
all this rich functionality without much
effort
so you mentioned a legacy application
many of the legacy applications were not
really microservices based they would
have been monolithic but a lot of what
you've been talking about especially
with the service mesh is directly
based on having multiple microservices
in the architecture in the system
so is that true so how did the legacy
application to convert that to modern
cloud architecture to convert that to
sas
what else is needed is there a break-up
process at some point you start to feel
the need for service mesh can you talk a
little bit more about that and is either
micro services architecture even
absolutely critical to having
to build a sas or convert a legacy to
sas
yeah i think it is important to go with
the micro services architecture let's go
through that right when do you feel the
need to create a services architecture
so as the legacy application becomes
larger and larger so nowadays there is a
lot of pressure to deliver applications
in the cloud
so why is it important because what's
happening is over a period of time when
the enterprise applications were
delivered on-premise it was very
expensive to upgrade
so
and also
every time you release a new software
the customers want upgrade and the
vendors were stuck with supporting
software that is almost 10 15 years old
so one of the things that cloud
applications provide is automatic
upgrade of all your applications to the
latest version and also for the vendor
to maintain only one version of the
software like keeping all the customers
in the latest and then providing them
with all the latest functionalities
that's a nice advantage of delivering
applications on the cloud so then the
question is can we deliver a big
monolithic applications on the cloud
the problem becomes a lot of the modern
cloud deployment architectures are
containers based we talked about the
scale and complexity
because when you are actually running
the customers applications on the cloud
let's say you have 500 customers in on
promise they all add 500 different
deployment now you are taking on the
burden of running all those deployment
in your own cloud
it is not easy so you need to
use kubernetes type of an architecture
to manage that level of
complex deployment in the cloud so
that's how you arrive at the decision of
you can't just simply running 500
monolithic deployment to run it
efficiently in the cloud you need to
have a containerized environment you
start going down that path not only that
many of the sas vendors have more than
one application so imagine running
several applications in its own legacy
way of running it you just cannot scale
so there are systematic ways of breaking
a monolithic applications into a
microservices architecture we can go
through that step let's delve into that
how does one go about it what is the
methodology are there patterns that
somebody can follow best practices
yeah so let me talk about some of the
basics right sas applications can
benefit from services architecture and
if you look at it almost all
applications
have many common platform components
some of the examples are
scheduling almost all of them have a
persistent storage
they all need a life cycle management
from desperad type of flow
and they all have to have data
connectors to multiple external system
virus scan document storage workflow
user management authorization
monitoring and observability
lucine type of search email etc right a
company that delivers multiple products
have no reason to build all of these
multiple times right and these are all
ideal candidates to be
delivered as a micro services and reused
across
the different sas applications one may
have
once you decide to create a services
architecture and you want to only focus
on building the service and then do as
good a job as possible and then putting
all of them together and deploying it
is given to someone else and that's
where the container is deployment come
into picture so typically what happens
is that one of the best practices
we all build containers and then deliver
it using what is called an artifactory
with appropriate version number
when you are actually deploying it you
specify all the different containers you
need and the compatible version numbers
all of these are put together as a part
and then delivered in the cloud that's
how it works and it is proven to work
well and the maturity level is pretty
high with widespread adoption in many
many
vendors so the other way also to look at
it is it's just a new architectural way
of developing application but the key
thing then is if you had a monolithic
application
how do you go about breaking it up so we
all see the benefit of it and i can walk
through
some of the aspects that you have to pay
attention to i think who might be it'd
be great if you use an example to get
into the next level of detail
suppose you have an hr application that
manages employees of a company
the employees may have you may have
anywhere between five to 100 attributes
per employees in different
implementation now let's assume
different personas who are asking for
different reports about employees with
different conditions so for example one
of the report could be you give me all
the employees who are at certain level
and making less than average
corresponding to their salary range
then another report could be
giving all the employees at a certain
level in certain location but were women
but at least five years in the same
level etc and let's assume that we have
a monolithic application that can
satisfy all these requirements now if
you want to break that monolithic
application into a micro service
and you just decided okay let me put
this employee
and its attribute and the management of
that in a separate microservice so
basically that micro service owns the
employee entity right anytime you want
to ask for an employee you got to go to
the micro service that seems like a
logical starting point
now because that service owns the
employee entity everybody else cannot
have a copy of it they will just need a
key to query that right let's assume
that is an employee
id or something like that
now when the report comes back
because you are running some other
services and you got the results back
the report may return either 10
employees or 100 000 employees
or it may
also
return as an output
two attributes per employee are under
attributes
so now when you come back from the back
end you will only have an employee id
now you have to populate all the other
information
about these attributes so now how do you
do that you need to go talk to this
employee service to get that information
so what would be the api designed for
that service and what will be the
payload do you has a list of employee
ids
or do you pass a list of attributes
or you make it a big uber api with the
list of employee ids and a list of
attributes if you call one at a time it
is too chatty but if you call it
everything together as one api it
becomes a very big payload but at the
same time if there are hundreds of
personas running that report what is
going to happen in the micro services it
will be very busy
creating a copy of the entity object
hundreds of times for the different
workloads so it becomes a massive memory
problem for that microservice so that's
a crux of the problem how do you design
the api
there is no single answer here so the
answer i'm going to give it in this
context may be having a distributed
cache where all the services sharing
that employee entity probably may make
sense but often that's what you need to
pay attention to right you have to go
look at all your workloads
what are the touch points
and then put the worst case hat and
think about the payload size chattiness
and whatnot if it is in the monolithic
application we would just simply be
traversing some data structure in memory
and we'll be reusing the pointer instead
of cloning the employee entity so it
will not have a much of a burden so we
need to be aware of this latency versus
throughput tradeoff right it is almost
always going to cost you more in terms
of latency when you are going to a
remote process
but the benefit you get is
in terms of scale out if the employee
service for example could be scaled into
100 scale out nodes now it can support
lot more workloads and lot more report
users which otherwise wouldn't be
possible in a scale-up situation or in a
monolithic situation so you offset the
loss of latency by a gain in throughput
and then by be able to support very
large workload so that's something you
want to be aware of but if you cannot
scale out then you don't gain anything
out of that
similarly
the other things you need to pay
attention are just a single tenant
application
it doesn't make sense to create a
services architecture you should try to
work on your algorithm to get a better
bound algorithms and try to scale up as
much as possible to get to a good
performance that satisfies all your
workloads but as you start introducing
multi-tenant so you don't know see you
are supporting lots of customers with
lots of users so you need to support
very large workload a single process
that scaled up cannot satisfy that level
of complexity and scale so that time
it's important to think in terms of
throughput and then scale out of various
services that's another important notion
right so multi-tenant is a key for a
services architecture so kumar you talk
in your example of an employee service
now and earlier you had hinted at more
platform services like search so an
employee service is not necessarily a
platform service that you would use in
other sas applications
so what is a justification for creating
an employee as a breakup of the monolith
even further beyond the use of platform
yeah that's a very good observation i
think the first starter would be to
create a platform components that are
common across multiple sas application
but once you get to the point sometimes
with that breakdown you still may not be
able to
satisfy the
large-scale workload in a scaled-up
process you want to start looking at how
you can break it further and there are
common ways of breaking even the
application level entities into
different microservices so the common
examples well at least in the domain
that i'm in
is to break it into a calculation engine
metadata engine
workflow engine user service and whatnot
similarly you may have a consolidation
account reconciliation
allocation and there are many many
application level concepts that you can
break it up further so that
at the end of the day what is the
service right you want to be able to
build it independently
you can reuse it and scale out as you
pointed out some of the reusable aspect
may not play a role here but then you
can scale out independently for example
you may have want to have a
multiple scaled out version of
calculation engine but maybe not so many
of metadata engine right and that is
possible with the kubernetes so
basically if you want to scale out
different parts of even the application
logic you may want to think about
content erasing it even further so this
assumes a multi-tenant deployment for
these microservices that's correct is
there any reason why you would still
want to do it if it was a single tenant
application
just to adhere to the two pizza team
model for example for developing and
deploying
right i think as i said for a single
tenant it doesn't justify creating this
complex architecture you want to
keep everything scale up as much as
possible and go to the particularly in
the java world as large as jvm as
possible and see whether you can satisfy
that because the workload is pretty well
known because the multi-tenant brings in
complexity of
like lots of
users from multiple companies who are
active at different point in time and
it's important to think in terms of
containerized world so i can go into
some of the other common issues you want
to pay attention to when you're creating
a service from a monolithic application
so the key aspect is each service should
have its own independent business
function or a logical ownership of the
entity that's one thing and you want to
avoid large common data structure that's
shared by a lot of services so it's
generally not a good idea in particular
if it is often needed leading to
chattiness or updated by multiple
services
you want to pay attention to payload
size of different api so api is the key
right when you are breaking it up you
need to
pay a lot of attention and go through
all your workloads and what are the
different apis and what are the payload
size
and chattiness of the api and you need
to be aware that there will be a latency
with a throughput and then
sometimes in a multi-tenant situation
you want to be aware of routing and
placement for example you want to know
which of these parts contain what
customers data you are not going to
replicate every customer's information
in every part so you need to cache that
information and you need to be able to
or do a service or do a lookup suppose
you have a workflow service there are
five copies of the service
and each copy runs the workflow for some
set of customers so you need to know how
to look that up there are updates that
need to be propagated to other services
you need to see how you are going to do
that the standard way of doing it
nowadays is using kafka event service
and that needs to be part of your
deployment architecture we already
talked about it single tenant is
generally you don't want to go through
this level of complexity for single
tenant and one thing that i keep
thinking about it is in the earlier days
when we did entity relationship modeling
for database there is a normalization
versus the denormalization tradeoff so
normalization we all know is good
because it addresses the notion of a
separation of concern
so this way the update is very efficient
you only update it in one place
and there is a clear ownership but then
when you want to retrieve the data
if it is extremely normalized you end up
paying price in terms of lot of joints
so services architecture is similar to
that right so when you want to combine
all the information you have to go to
all these services to collate the
information and present it so it helps
to think in terms of normalization
versus denormalization right so do you
want to have some kind of a read
replicas where all these informations
are collated so that way the read
replica addresses some of the clients
that are asking for information from
collection of services session
management is another critical aspect
you want to pay attention to once you
are authenticated how do you pass that
information around similarly all the
services may want to share
database information connection pool
where to log and all of that there's a
lot of configuration that you want to
share and between the service mesh or or
introducing a configuration service by
itself you can address some of those
problem given all this complexity should
people also pay attention to how many is
too many certainly there's a lot of
benefit
to not having microservices
so and there are benefits to having them
but there must be a sweet spot is there
anything you can comment on the number
i think it's important to
look at service mesh and other complex
deployment because they provide benefit
but at the same time the deployment
becomes complex like you are devops and
when you suddenly need to take on extra
work right see anything more than five i
would say is non-trivial and need to be
designed carefully i think in the
beginning
most of the deployments may not have all
the complex the sidecars and service
mesh and whatnot but over a period of
time as you scale to thousands of
customers and then you have a multiple
applications
all of them are deployed in and
delivered on the cloud
it is important to
look at the full strength of the cloud
deployment architecture thank you kumar
that certainly covers several topics
the one that strikes me though as very
critical for a multi-tenant application
is ensuring that data is isolated and
there's no leakage
between your deployment which is for
multiple customers
can you talk more about that and
patterns to ensure this isolation
yeah sure
when it comes to platform service they
are stateless and we are not really
worried about this issue but when you
break the application
into multiple services
and then the application data
needs to be shared between different
services so how do you go about doing it
so there are two common patterns one is
if there are multiple services who need
to
update and also read the data like all
the read write workloads have to be
supported through multiple services
the most logical way to do it is using a
radius type of a distributed cache
then the question is if you are using a
distributed cache and you are also
storing data from multiple tenants how
is this possible so typically what you
do is you have a tenant id comma object
id as a key so that that way even though
they're mixed up they are still well
separated
but if you're concerned you can actually
even keep that data in memory encrypted
using tenant specific key right so that
way
once you read from the distributed cache
and then before
the other services use them they can
decrypt using the tenant specific key
that's one thing if you want to add an
extra layer of security but
but the other pattern is typically only
one service wants the update but all
others need a copy of that the regular
interval are almost at real time so the
way it happens is the ownership service
still updates the data and then passes
all the update as an event through kafka
stream and all the other services
subscribe to that but here what happens
is you need to have a clone of that
object everywhere else so that they can
perform that update it's basically
that you cannot avoid but in our example
what we talked about all of them will
have a copy of the employee object as
and when an update happens to an
employee those updates are propagated
and they apply it locally those are the
two design patterns which are commonly
adapted so we spent quite some time
talking about how the sas application is
composed
from multiple platform services and in
some cases striping the business
functionality itself into a micro
service
especially for platform services i'd
like to talk more about
how do you decide whether you build it
or you know you buy it and buying could
be subscribing to an existing cloud
vendor or maybe looking across your own
organization to see if someone else has
that specific platform service
what's your experience about going
through this process
i know this is a pretty common problem i
don't think people get it right but you
know what i can talk about my own
experience it's important within a large
organization everybody recognizes there
shouldn't be any duplication effort and
one should design it in a way
that allows for sharing that's a nice
thing about the modern containerized
world because the artifactory allows for
distribution of these containers
in a different version in a easy way to
be shared across the organization when
you're actually deploying even though
the different products may be even using
different versions of these containers
in the deployment country you can
actually speak what version do you want
to use
so that way
different versions doesn't pose a
problem so many companies don't even
have a common artifactory for sharing
and that should be fixed and it's an
important investment they should take it
seriously so i would say like platform
services everybody should strive to
share as much as possible and we already
talked about it there are a lot of
common services like workflow and
document service and all of that when it
comes to build versus buy the other
things that people don't understand is
even the multiple platforms or multiple
operating systems also is not an issue
for example the latest.net version is
compatible with kubernetes it's not that
you only need all linux versions of
containers so even if there is a good
service that you want to consume and if
it is in windows you can still consume
it so we need to pay attention to it
even if you want to build it on your own
it's okay to get started with the
containers that are available and you
can go ahead and buy and consume it
quickly and then over a period of time
you can replace it so
i would say the decision is purely based
on i mean you should look in the
business interest to see is it our core
business to build such a thing and also
does our priority allow us to do it
or just go and get one and then deploy
it because the standard way of deploying
containers
allows for easy consumption even if you
buy externally what else do you need to
ensure though before you decide to you
know quote unquote by externally what
compliance or security aspects should
you pay attention to
yeah i mean i think that's an important
question so
the security is very key these
containers should support a tls and if
there is data they should support
different types of an encryption for
example there are so we can talk about
some of the security aspect of it that's
one thing and then it should be
compatible with your cloud architecture
let's say you are going to use service
mesh and there should be a way to deploy
the container that you are buying should
be compatible with that we didn't talk
about api gateway yet if you're going to
use an api gateway and there should be
an easy way that it conforms to our
gateway but security is an important
aspect and i can talk about that in
general there are three types of
encryption right encryption at rest and
encryption in transit
and encryption in memory encryption
addressed means when you store the data
in a disk and that data should be kept
encrypted encryption is translated when
a data moves between services
and it should go in an encrypted way
and encryption in memory is when the
data is in memory even the data
structure should be encrypted and the
third one is the encryption memory is
like most of the vendors they don't do
it because it's pretty expensive but
there are some critical
parts of it they do keep it encrypted in
memory but when it comes to
encryption in transit the modern
standard is tls 1.2 and also there are
different algorithms requiring different
levels of
encryption using 256 bits and so on
and it should conform to the is standard
possible right that's for the transit
encryption and also there are a
different types of encryption algorithms
symmetric versus asymmetric and using
certificate authority and all of that
so there is a rich literature and there
is a lot of well understood patents here
and it's not that difficult to adapt on
the modern standard for this and if you
use histo type of service mesh adapting
tls becomes easier because
the ny proxy performs the duty as a tls
endpoint so it makes it easy but when it
comes to
encryption address there are fundamental
questions you want to ask in terms of
design
do you encrypt the data in the
application and then send the encrypted
data to this persistent storage
or do you rely on the database you send
the data unencrypted using tls and then
encrypt the data in disk right that's
one question typically people use two
types of key one is called an envelope
key another is called a data key anyway
envelope key is used to encrypt the data
key and then the data key is is what is
used to encrypt the data
and the envelope key is what is rotated
often
and the data key is rotated very rarely
because you need to touch every data to
decrypt it but rotation of both are
important and what frequency are you
rotating all those keys that's an
another design question and then you
have different environments for a
customer you may have a desk prod the
data is encrypted how do you move the
encrypted data between these tenants and
that's an important question you need to
have a good design for so these are good
compliance asks for any platform service
you're choosing and of course for any
service you are building as well that's
good so you mentioned the api gateway
and the fact that this platform service
needs to be compatible what does that
mean so typically what happens when you
have lots of micro services right each
of the micro services have their own
apis
to perform any useful business function
you need to
call a sequence of apis from all of
these services like as we talked earlier
if the number of services explodes you
need to understand the api from all of
these and also most of the vendors
support lots of clients
now each one of these clients have to
understand all these services all these
apis but even though it serves an
important function from an internal
complexity management and skill purpose
from an external business perspective
this level of complexity and exposing
that to external client doesn't make
sense this is where the api gateway
comes in apa gateway acts as an
aggregator of these apis from these
multiple services
and expose a simple api
which performs
the holistic business function so these
clients then can become simpler so the
clients call into the api gateway api
which either directly routes sometimes
to an api of a service or it does an
orchestration it may call anywhere from
five to ten apis from these different
services and all of them don't have to
be exposed to all the clients that's an
important function performed by ap
gateway it's very critical to start
having an api gateway once you have a
non-trivial number of micro services
the other functions it also performs are
it does what is called a rate limiting
meaning if you want to enforce certain
rule like this service cannot be invoked
more than certain time and sometimes it
does a lot of analytics of which api is
called how many times and authentication
all
all those functions are so you don't
have to authenticate at every service so
it gets authenticated at the gateway we
turn around and call the internal api
it's an important component of a cloud
architecture the aggregation is that
something that's configured with the api
gateway there are some gateways where it
is possible to configure but that
standards are still being established
more often this is written as a code got
it the other thing you talked about
earlier was the
different types of environments so dev
test and production is that a standard
with sas that you provide these
different
types and what is the implicit
function of each of them right i think
the different vendors have different
contracts and they provide as part of
selling the product there are different
contracts established like every
customer gets certain type of tenants so
why do we need this if we think about
even an on-premise world there will be a
typically a production deployment and
once somebody buys a software to get to
a production it takes anywhere from
several weeks to several months so what
happens during that time right so they
buy a software
they start doing a development they
first convert the requirements into a
whatever it's a model
and then build that model
there will be a long phase of
development process then it goes through
different types of testing user
acceptance testing and whatnot
performance testing then it gets
deployed in production so in on-premise
world typically you will have multiple
environments development test and uat
and prod and whatnot so when we come to
the
cloud world customers expect a similar
functionality because unlike on-premise
world the vendor now manages
in an on-premise world if you had 500
customers and each one of those
customers had four machines now these
2000 machines have to be managed by the
vendor because they are now
administering all those aspects right in
the cloud without significant level of
tooling and automation
supporting all these customers as they
go through these lifecycle
is almost impossible so you need to have
a very formal
definition of what these things mean
just because they move from on-premise
to cloud they don't want to give up on
going through this broad cycle it still
takes time to
build a model test a model go through an
user acceptance and whatnot so almost
all sas vendors
have these type of concept and i have
tooling around one of the differing
aspects may be
how do you move data from one
environment to another either how do you
automatically refresh from one round to
another what kind of data gets promoted
from one to another so the refresh
semantics becomes very critical and do
they have an exclusion sometimes a lot
of the customers provide automatic
refresh from prod to dev automatic
promotion from test to
test impul and all of that but this is
very critical to build and expose it to
your customer and make them understand
and make them part of that because all
the things they used to do in on-premise
now they have to do it in the cloud and
if you had to scale to hundreds and
thousands of customers you need to have
a pretty good tooling makes sense
the next question i had along the same
wayne was
disaster recovery
and
then perhaps talk about these different
types of environment would it be fair to
assume that doesn't have to apply to a
dev environment or a test environment
but only a
more often when they design it dr is an
important requirement and i think we'll
get to
what applies to what environment in a
short time
but let me first talk about dr so dr has
got two important metrics one is called
an rto which is time objective another
is called rp which is a point objective
so rto is like how much
time it will take to recover from the
time of disaster do you bring up the dr
site within 10 hours 2 hours 1 hour
so that is clearly documented rpo is
after the disaster how much data is lost
is it 0 or 1 hour of data 5 minutes of
data so it's important to
understand what these metrics are and
understand how your design works and
clearly articulate these metrics they're
part of it and i think different values
for this matrix call for different
designs so that's very important so
typically right it's very important for
prod environment to support dr and most
of the vendors support even the dev and
test product also because
it's all implemented using clusters and
all the clusters with their associated
persistent storage are backed up using
an appropriate the rtvo time may be
different between different environments
it's okay for development to come up
little slowly but rpo objective is
typically common between all these
environments along with dr the
associated aspects are high availability
and scale up and out i mean our
availability is provided automatically
by
most of the cloud architecture because
if a part goes down and another part is
brought up and services the request and
so on typically you may have a redundant
pods which can service the request when
the routing automatically happens scale
up and out are integral to an
application algorithm whether it can do
a scale up and out it's very critical to
think about it during the design time
what about upgrades and deploying next
versions
is there a cadence so test or dev gets
updated first and then production i
assume that would have to follow the
customers timelines in terms of being
able to ensure that their application is
ready for accepted as production the
industry
expectation is you know downtime and
there are different companies that have
different methodologies to achieve that
so typically you will have almost all
companies have different types of
software delivery we call it art fix
service pack
or future bearing releases and whatnot
right art fixes are the critical things
that need to go in
at some point right i mean i think as
close to the
incident as possible and service packs
are regularly scheduled patches and
releases are
also regularly scheduled but at a much
lower cadence compared to service pack
often this is closely tied with strong
slas companies have promised to the
customers like four nine availability
fine and availability and whatnot
there are good techniques to achieve
zero downtime but the software has to be
designed in a way that allows for that
right can each container be do you have
a bundle bill which contains all the
containers together or do you deploy
each container separately and then what
about if you have a schema changes how
do you take advantage how do you upgrade
that because every customer schema have
to be upgraded a lot of times schema
upgrade is probably the most challenging
one sometimes you need to write a
compensating code to account for so that
it can work on the world schema and the
new schema and then at run time you
upgrade the schema there are techniques
to do that
zero downtime is typically achieved
using what is called a rolling upgrade
as different clusters are upgraded to
the new version and because of the high
availability you can upgrade the other
parts to the latest version so
there are well established patterns here
but it's important to spend enough time
thinking through it and design it
appropriately so
in terms of the upgrade cycles or
deployment how critical are customer
notifications
just letting the customer know what to
expect when i think almost all companies
have a well-established protocol for
this like they all have signed contracts
about like in terms of downtime and
notification and all of that and there
are well established pattern for it but
i think what is important is if you are
changing the behavior of a ui
or any functionality
it's important to have a very specific
communication let's say you are going to
have a downtime friday from 5 to 10
and often this is exposed even in the ui
that they may get an email but most of
the companies now start to address that
in the enterprise software itself like
what time is it but i agree with you i
mean i don't have a pretty good answer
but most of the companies do have
assigned contracts in how they
communicate and often it is through
email and to a specific representative
of the company and also through the ui
but the key thing is if you are changing
the behavior you need to walk the
customer through it very carefully
make sense so we've talked about key
design principles
micro service composition for the
application
and certain customer experiences and
expectations i wanted to next talk a
little bit about regions and
observability so in terms of deploying
to multiple regions
how important is that how many regions
across the world
in your experience makes sense and then
how does one facilitate the ci cd
necessary to be able to do this
sure let me walk through it slowly first
let me talk about the regions right when
you're a multinational company you're a
large vendor delivering to customers in
different geographies regions play a
pretty critical role right your data
centers in different regions help
achieve that so regions are chosen
typically to cover broad geography you
will typically have a us europe
australia sometimes even singapore
south america and so on and there are
very strict data privacy rules that need
to be enforced these different regions
because sharing anything between these
regions is strictly prohibited and you
are to conform to you have to work with
all your legal and others to make sure
what is to clearly document what is
shared and what is not shared and having
data centers in different regions allow
you to
enforce this strict data privacy
so typically the terminology used is
what is called an availability region so
these are all the different geographical
locations where there are cloud data
centers and different regions offer
different service qualities right in
terms of not only in terms of latency
see some products may not be offered in
certain regions and also the cost may be
different for large vendors and cloud
providers these regions are existing
across the globe they have to enforce
the governance rules of data sharing and
other aspects as required by the
respective governments but within a
region you have what is called an
availability zone so this refers to an
isolated data center within a region
and then each availability zone can also
have a multiple data center so this is
needed for a dr purpose for every
availability zone you will have an
associated availability zone for a dr
purpose right and i think there is a
common vocabulary and common standard
that is being adapted by the different
cloud vendors as i was saying right now
unlike on-premise in the cloud
in on-premise world you will have like
there are a thousand customers each
customer may add like five to ten
administrators so
let's say that's equivalent to five
thousand administrators now the role of
that five thousand administrator has to
be played by the single vendor who's
delivering an application in the cloud
it's impossible to do it without
significant amount of automation and
tooling right almost all vendors enlarge
an observability and monitoring
framework this has gotten pretty
sophisticated right i mean it all starts
with how much logging that's happening
and particularly it becomes complicated
when it becomes micro services let's say
there is a user request and that goes
and runs a report and if it touches
let's say seven or eight services
as it goes through all these services
previously maybe in a monolithic
application it was easy to log different
parts of the application now this
request is touching all these services
maybe multiple times
how do you log that right it's important
so most of the softwares have thought
through it from a design time they
established a common context id or
something and that is law so you have a
multi-tenant software and you have a
specific user within the tenant and a
specific request
so all that have to be all that context
have to be provided with all your logs
and then need to be tracked through all
these services right
what's happening is these logs are then
analyzed there are multiple vendors like
elk sumo logic and splunk and many many
vendors who provide
very good monitoring and observability
frameworks like these logs are analyzed
and they almost provide a real-time
dashboard showing what is going on in
the system you can even create a
multi-dimensional
analytical
dashboard on top of that to slice and
dice by
various aspect of which cluster which
customer which tenant what request is
having problem and that can be
then you can then define thresholds and
then based on the threshold you can then
generate alerts and then there are page
duty type of a software which i think
there's another software called panda
all of these can be used in conjunction
with these alerts to send text messages
and whatnot right i mean it has gotten
pretty sophisticated and i think almost
all vendors have a pretty rich
observable depraved framework and
without that it's very difficult to
efficiently operate the cloud and you
basically want to
figure out much earlier than any issue
before your customer even perceives it
and i assume capacity planning is also
critical it could be termed under
observability or not but that would be
something else that the devops
folks have to pay attention to
completely agree how do you know what
capacity you need when you have these
complex and scale needs right lots of
customers with each customers having
lots of
users
so you can first over provision it and
have a very large system then it cuts
your bottom line right then you are
spending a lot of money if you have an
under capacity then it causes all kinds
of performance issues and stability
issues right
so what is the right way to do it the
only way to do it is through having a
good observability and monitoring
framework and then use that as a
feedback loop to constantly upgrade your
framework and then kubernetes deployment
where that allows us to dynamically
scale the parts
helps significantly in this aspect even
the customers are not going to ramp up
on day one they also probably will
slowly ramp up on their users and
whatnot and it's very
important to pay very close attention to
what's going on in your production and
then constantly use the capabilities
that is provided by these cloud
deployment to scale up and down right
but you need to have all the framework
in place right you have to constantly
know let's say you have 25 clusters in
each clusters you have 10 machines and
10 machines you have
lots of parts and you have different
workloads right like you use a login
user running some calculation user
running some reports so each one of the
workloads you need to deeply understand
how it is performing
and different customers may be using
different sizes of your model for
example in my world we have a
multi-dimensional database allow
customers to create configurable type of
database one customer have five
dimension another customer can have 15
dimension one customer can have a
dimension with hundred members another
customer can have a largest dimension of
million members
so 100 users versus 10 000 users there
are different customers come in
different sizes and shape and they
stress the systems in in different way
and of course we need to have a pretty
strong qa and performance lab which
think through all these
using synthetic models makes the system
go through all these
different workloads but nothing like
observing the production and taking the
feedback and adjusting your capacity
accordingly so starting to wrap up now
and we've gone through several complex
topics here
while that's complex itself to build the
sas application and deploy it and have
customers onboard it at the same time
this is just one piece of the puzzle at
the customer site most customers choose
between multiple best-of-breed sas
applications
so what about extensibility what about
creating the ability to integrate your
application with other sas applications
and then also integration with analytics
that lets customers introspect as they
go that is one of the challenging issues
like a typical customer may have
multiple sas applications
and then you end up building an
integration at the customer side you may
then go and buy a pass service where you
write your own code to integrate data
from all these or
you buy a data warehouse that pulls data
from these multiple applications
and then put one of the bi tools on top
of that so data warehouse acts like an
aggregator for integrating with multiple
sas applications like snowflake or
any of the data virus vendors where they
pull data from multiple sas application
and you build an analytical applications
on top of that and that's a trend where
things are moving but if you want to
build your own application that pulls
data from multiple sas application
again it is all possible because almost
all vendors in the sas application they
provide ways to extract data
but then it leads to a lot of complex
things like
how do you script that how do you
schedule that and so on but it is
important to have a data warehouse
strategy
you have a bi and analytical strategy
and there are a lot of possibilities and
there are a lot of capabilities even
they are available in the cloud right
whether it is amazon redshift or
snowflake there are many or google
bigtable there are many data warehouses
in the cloud
and all the bi vendors talk to all of
these cloud so it's almost
not necessary to have any data center
footprint where you build
complex applications or deploy your own
data warehouse or anything like that so
we covered several topics though is
there anything you feel that we did not
talk about that is absolutely critical
to
i don't think so no thanks kanchan i
mean for this opportunity to talk about
this i think we covered a lot one last
point i would add is
you know sre and devops it's a new thing
right i mean they are absolutely
critical for success of your cloud maybe
that's one aspect we didn't talk about
it so devops automation
all the run books they create
and investing heavily in devops
organization is an absolute must because
they are the key folks who
if there is a vendor cloud vendor who's
delivering four or five sas applications
to thousands of customers the devops
basically runs the show they are an
important part of the organization and
it's important to have a good set of
people how can people contact you i
think they can contact me through
linkedin to start with my company email
but i would prefer them they start with
linkedin thank you so much for this
today i really enjoyed this conversation
oh thank you kanjin for taking time
thanks all for listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening